Hi there. My name is Randy Fay. I'm one of the
maintainers of the DDEV project and I want to give you a tour today of DDEV on
Windows subsystem for Linux, WSL2. DDEV has supported WSL2 for a number of
years but it's just gotten better all the time and in our latest release we
even have an installer that installs it all the different ways that you can
use. So I am going to go ahead and step through that. First of all let's just
make sure that you might not be familiar with DDEV. DDEV is a Docker-based
local development environment. It's mostly for web developers but it does all of
the web things for you. It does node and NPM and it does PHP. It does all those
things for you in a predictable, containerized environment. PHP and node
developers use it. HTML, developers use it. It can be used a lot of different
ways. You run the website on your own local computer. There's basically no
configuration of the computer and you can run many projects or websites at
the same time and each one can have a different configuration and your team can
share that configuration and check it in. Because Docker does the lifting you
don't have to even have anything like PHP or Composer on your host computer and
deal with those complexities. DDEV has been around for quite a few years now
and it's had first-class Mac, Linux, Windows and WSL2 support for really quite a
long time. It works the same on every platform.
WSL2 is a real Linux kernel and the instances of that of the Linux
distribution built into all supports, all versions of Windows. This is an amazing
thing that Microsoft would do this and they've been working at it now for it must
be almost 10 years and they've done quite a good job. It's a different world but
it's right there in Windows and it's quite good and after all these years the
level of maturity is quite excellent. Nothing's perfect in any context but it's
great stuff. Let's just talk about the WSL2 advantages and disadvantages. I
love WSL2 but I'm a Linux guy from way back so for me it's having my favorite
Linux right there in the midst of a very mature and wonderful GUI operating
system. That's great for me. On the advantage side it gives me Linux with
all the tools and power of Linux right there available to me anytime. With DDEV
it's got great performance and web serving and you're working with an
environment much like where you'll deploy to. It is worth working in
environment that is like your deployment environment. Of course DDEV already
does that for you inside the container but for you to work inside to use the
command line with Linux tools is a great benefit because that's where your
that's where your website will be deployed. So the disadvantages. Number one is the
same thing. You've got Linux on your Windows machine. You've already had a
thousand and thousand and thousand things to learn and remember and now
there's a whole different context with Linux. So and those context switches
between the the Windows side and the WSL side and the fact that there are two
different file systems is you know it's extra complexity. So it requires
learning and patience with yourself while you learn it. And the third
thing is because the WSL 2 or the Linux file system it's called EXT4 is so
much better for web serving and really better for anything that is a lot of
files and you really have to work in the WSL 2 file system and all of the
standard editors are perfectly capable of doing that. So you can use your
favorite Windows editors but you need to use them against the WSL 2 file
system. Microsoft built oh good old NTFS for Microsoft Word for huge files a
few huge files and not for web apps but I'll show you how to do that as we go
forward. So let's just take a look at the docs and what we're going to do here.
There's a quick a quick doc and there's there's more extensive docs but what
we're going to do is we're going to go to the "get started" page and we're going
to go through all the things on my machine which is pretty close to not having
anything on it. I skipped the part where I would have to reboot so that we can
have a little continuity. So let's go take a look right quick at the at the get
started page here. So here's our "get started" page, ddev.com/get-
started and we're going to choose Windows here and here's the process that
we're going to do. We've got three steps basically here. We're going to do a
WSL-install then we're going to install an Ubuntu distro that is get the
name deed of Ubuntu by the way is a classic distribution of Linux that has
been around it must be close to 20 years that is very very well maintained and
stable and very widely known. So that's why we prefer it. There are there are
other ways to do other things but we're trying to keep you on the straight
narrow here. So then we'll take a look and make sure that we've got our new
distro going. Then we're going to run the deed of installer will download and
run the deed of installer and then we will create a project in the in there. So
that's the steps that we're going to do. So let's go ahead and do those. I'm going
to switch over here and I'm going to open up the Windows terminal running
PowerShell. It doesn't really matter what you're running here. PowerShell or CMD
or get-bash. They'll all work the same. We're not doing anything particularly
exciting. We're going to do a WSL-install and that did an escalation. Had I
been doing that for the very first time on this machine after it did the
install that we're looking at here it would force me to reboot and that's the
part that we happen to be skipping in in my case. It also sometimes gives a bit
of a bogus error message saying that it was missing some component because it's
waiting for a reboot. So this has installed now the WSL-2 component with the
current version and now it's getting the distro. But if I remember right it's
not going to know what to do with the distro and we're still going to have to
install the Ubuntu distro ourselves.
No, I didn't do that this time. It depends on the state of your machine whether
it does that. I'm going to set my local user here. I always use our fade and let's
see if I can type it correctly. And so there I am and you'll see that it landed
me in the machine, in the freshly created machine here. I don't really want to
be there. I'll show you this in a minute. I'm going to do what we suggest and
create one called DDO because the state of my machine it was able to just
automatically create the Ubuntu distro without the other processes. So I'm
going to say WSL-dash install-dash-name. Let's see we're going to say Ubuntu-dash-name-DDO.
So we're going to just create one named DDO and the name doesn't matter. It's
just to if you have more than one for whatever reason that may help you to
remember which one is which. So we're just doing the same thing again that
it automatically was doing with the Ubuntu distro and then we're going to
delete the other one because we don't need it.
Okay and it landed us in the Windows home which I don't really want it to be
but I'm going to exit out of there. Now I'm going to do a WSL-L-V and we're
going to see that we have two distros and they're both version two. If you see a
version one there then something has gone terribly wrong and you would do a
WSL-dash-set default version two and then you would have to recreate. So but
that version two is the default. So if you're setting up WSL these days it's
there and it's already the default and all those things. So what I'm going to do
now is I'm going to set my DDEV one to be the default just makes things
slightly easier and now you see the star is on DDEV and now I'm going to get rid
of the other one with an unregister command and we only needed the one. So
there we are we have a DDEV distro. I am going to close this PowerShell and
open Windows terminal. Windows terminal if you haven't seen it around it's
now a standard part of Windows and it's really quite an excellent step forward
and when you install a distro you automatically get the things that you really
need so it creates a new DDEV entry there. So I can just pop that and that's
what that's my favorite thing to use for accessing the distro and you'll
notice that when it opens a distro it opens it in the home directory which is
where we want it to be. So right now this distro doesn't have much on it and
so the thing that we're going to do is we're going to run the DDEV installer. So
let's go and we will go to github.com, DDEV, and we'll go to releases, we'll
get the latest one. We are on an AMD64 Windows machine which most of you are
as well and so we want the DDEV Windows AMD64 installer for the latest
release. So I'm going to get that one and then we're just going to run that
install. So it did elevate, it did a UAC prompt to give us privileges to do
this install and now I'm going to go and you see we have three choices here for
the DDEV installation type and we'll talk about the other two choices right now.
We do recommend the Docker CE approach and WSL2 but the others are totally
valid and we'll talk about those toward the end of this session. So we've only
got one distro right now so it's only offering us one choice here and all the
normal things that one of these does and it's going to go through and it's
mostly spending all of its time configuring that distro that we installed. We
can actually watch it do it here. It's installing the required Linux packages,
downloading them, installing them. These are things that we used to have a fairly
complex PowerShell script to do that was a little awkward to run and now these
are done by the by the installer for you. So it takes actually the first time
you run this it has to install, it has to download and install everything but
after that your distro has most of the things in it and you can rerun this, you
can do an upgrade with it, you can rerun it as many times as you want and it
does no harm. You can run it on the same distro again again again and it does
no harm. So there we go. On the last page you see that we have a check box here
to say, consider launching, consider visiting our support page. So we will do
that. We do need your support. GitHub is a free and open source project with two
people working all the time on it and a huge community making it happen but we
need your sponsorship and we want to become a sustainable project. So please do
consider supporting it yourself or getting your organization to support
DDEV. Now there we are. We have finished that installation and now we're going to
go and do a trivial install. So we're going to go back here to the DDEV distro.
I'll just open it again. Here's the DDEV distro. Now we can see that DDEV is
installed here and working and Docker is working. So we have all the all the
piece parts that we need to go forward. I always make my projects in a subdirectory
called Workspace. A lot of people use a subdirectory called Sites. I recommend you use a lower
case S for that if you do. What we're going to do for our first round is we're just going
to create a very very simple PHP file and turn that into a project because it shows you
very quickly what we need to do. So I'm going to create a project called I'll call it test.
I always use the I always use junk personally but I'm going to use tests for this one and
I am going to put in there a file. I'm going to put a PHP file in there. Well actually
I'm just going to put it I'm just going to put an HTML file. We're just going to put an
index.html. The DDEV is very happy to have an index.html. Now I'm going to do a DDEV
config and I can use just the defaults here. I could have done a DDEV config dash dash
auto. Now I'm going to do a DDEV start and it's going to ask if it can do the usage
statistics and such. We'll say yes and now it has to pull the images that it needs. This
process of pulling the images is usually not very annoying. We are doing this from scratch
the very very first time and so it's getting those but the next time we go to a project
that uses the same images which is usually all of our projects using the same images.
It doesn't have to download those are down those are now on your machine. So even though
this looks like a bit of work the first time around it's not that bad because every project
is sharing the images and so it works out it works out fine. We can get going pretty quickly
of course if you're on slower internet this will be this will be slower than my downloads
here and you can have a cup of coffee. This internet doesn't let me have that cup of
coffee for the downloads.
Okay here it is it's done. I'm going to do a DDEV describe like it says like it suggests.
So here are the basics of this project. Here's the main URL test.ddev.site. The Docker
platform is WZL2 Docker CE. There are details about the individual containers and of course
we can access our project four different ways. One is via the HTTPS trusted HTTPS. One is via
the direct to the web you are the web IP address and port and then we can also use HTTPS
and sometimes there's a reason to do that. I'm going to use the regular HTTPS so I'm just going
to say DDEV launch which is how most of us do that most of the time and you see we have we
are now a page here with our index.html and our URL is a trusted URL because DDEV in the install
process installed all the things that we need for that and we have a valid certificate
that the browser trusts here. So we have created a truly trivial little project by doing that
and there we are. So now I would like to do a slightly so we've just done all the things. We
did a whole project. We made a whole project. It's running and we have it in front of us.
Now I'm going to do a slightly more complex project. I'm just going to do a Drupal 11 project
because that's what's in my fingers and I'm going to do a DDEV config and this is all. Let me
just show you here the many ways that you could do whatever you wanted to here. Here's a section
in the docs called CMS Quick Starts. You can just search in the search per Quick Start and you see
look at all of those that are just examples of what can be done. These are maintained examples
that have automated testing but there are many many other uses of DDEV that are not listed here.
Lots of people use it for lots and lots of things but these are the ones that have a recipe listed
here in the Quick Start and I'm going to use the Drupal 11 recipe here.
So I'm going to do a DDEV config, dash dash project, type equals Drupal 11, dash dash dot
root equals web. I could have done this manually but I usually just type in the things that I know
because I do it often and now I'm going to do a DDEV composer create project,
Drupal slash recommended project. So this is using Composer create project under the good
to do all the things that you need to do to get a project going with Drupal 11.
There are obviously many ways to do this. I could have checked out. I could have checked out a
project. In fact, I do that often or we could do the Composer method which is what we have here.
Composer create project happens to start the project. So
there it is. It's already done and now if I do a DDEV launch here
I can actually go through the process here and I'll just do that. Usually I would use Drush at
this point to do a very quick install but I will do a manual install here using the web UI.
You see that it's already configured with the database and things like that. That's a convenience
feature that DDEV provides that it does all of the provides automatically all of the database
configuration and that kind of thing for you.
Okay, we'll just fill in a couple of things here.
In this case, we don't need updates so we will save it and
there's our project all set up for us. It's a great thing to have a project
to just experiment with here and this is fully functional project here. So we'll use this project
in a couple of minutes for demonstrating Xdebug. I wish you were here right now because I'd ask
you if you have any questions but let's switch back and see how much I left out of our presentation.
So what we did was we did a WSL-dash install and on my machine that accidentally created a
distro called Ubuntu that we didn't need. We did a WSL-dash update to make sure we were on the
current version of WSL. Then we created a distro named DDEV which is what we've been using,
where we were working just right here is where we were working in a distro called DDEV. It's
an Ubuntu distro. So you can see that this is an Ubuntu 24.4 distro and then we ran the Windows
installer and we basically chose the defaults in all the cases there. So that was our experiment
that we just did. So here's the junk project that I didn't do. I did a test project and then
here's a typo 3 example. I did a Drupal example instead and then I do want to show you a couple of
things that you can do so that you're familiar with some of the tools that are out there.
There are many tools but if I just go DDEV you'll see that we have a whole bunch of commands
that you don't have to know all about. I can do a DDEV, let me just do this.
I'm going to do a DDEV export, export, vb-pile equals dot, our balls, dv dot sql dot gz.
And that will save our database into that file. I can do a DDEV snapshot
and that will create a database snapshot which is a binary image of the database.
I recommend that you keep snapshots of all your projects because you never know what can happen
on your machine and these are regular files instead of the Docker volume where these things are
usually stored. DDEV described we already showed. Always very useful. DDEV list shows you your
projects that you have. We have two projects, a Drupal 11 and a base PHP project.
What else did I promise to show you? Stop, power off, mysql snapshot. When you want to stop a project
let's go back to the test project and I'm just going to say DDEV stop and I could have from anywhere
said "ddev stop test" and it would have stopped the distro or the project name "test".
So that now is stopped and it shows it is stopped.
One of my favorites is DDEV mysql because I'm familiar on the command line so I can do a show
tables here. What did I do wrong there? I didn't have a typo so I can just do a quick set of
things like that. But DDEV has any number of other database browsers. A lot of people really like
to have a GUI database browser and if you just search for database in the DDEV docs it'll link you
to. There must be seven or eight different browsers. There's one for every taste and the PhpStorm
and at VS Code integrations that we will look at in just a moment also have database integrations.
So there's all those things and then a DDEV power off, DDEV power off shuts off all of your
sites and all of your and any of the supporting containers like the router and the SSH agent
so that everything is stopped. So okay so I'm going to start that one back up again and we will move
on. It's worth exploring those various tools. There's very many of them there.
Okay now we're going to do PhpStorm and we're going to connect up to this
connect up to this project and take a look at the files and then we're going to
we're going to turn on Xdebug and listen for it. So I'll see if I can do this correctly.
It's possible that I won't be able to because I was fooling with it already today. So let's see
how we do. And I already had a distro when I was fooling it with it called DDEV. So I'm going to
here I am in PhpStorm and I want to open and the way you open in most apps is
in this in this finder or picker window we will see that there's Linux down here and we want Linux
and we want DDEV and we want home and one of the first things that I usually I'll show you in
just a second. I usually make that a favorite but we're working on D11. D11 is the folder that we're
going to use and you'll see that you see the PhpStorm knows how to navigate that and has worked
all of that out. It wants to exclude the folders so I'll say sure you can do that
and it did elevate in order to do that that you couldn't see I don't believe.
And it's been doing all the things that we want it to do. Let me just show you what I was saying
here. If I go into the windows explorer here and I go to Linux->DDEV->home->rfay.
Arfe, oh here I want to just be in home. I like to drag that into my favorites very early when
I'm working with something so I'll bring that over here and maybe put it right and not there.
Oh it's got to go up higher here sorry. So I'm going to bring it right over here. You see I've
already got an "rfay" for a different one but we're going to go here and we're going to take workspace
and bring that over here into the favorites as well and we'll bring our test project, our D11 project
over there as well so we'll have quick access to those.
And now that will be available anytime we're doing an open in any tool that we're using any
editor or anything else. So okay so we have it open now. We have our files, all of them.
Here's the web and the index.php and I can edit and work on these all day long and I can use
the git facilities of PhpStorm and I can use the terminal. Here's the terminal. You see the
terminal has already got this is already using the terminal inside WSL2 inside our distro. So we can
do it DDEV describe here and do all the things that we need to do. And now I'm going to demonstrate
if you're with me this far you're probably already familiar with PhpStorm. So I won't demonstrate
all the features of PhpStorm but the next thing that I want to do is install the DDEV plugin because
it's really very nice. Very well maintained. We'll go here into settings and we'll go into plugins
and go to Marketplace and DDEV and this is the one that we want right here.
And I don't know for sure if we have to turn off to stop and start PhpStorm here.
But you'll see that this DDEV detected is coming from the extension and that's showing us all
the things. I don't know what the checking PHP installation is, what that message is or where it's
coming from. But it looks like it's done. There we go. So the extension went in and found that DDEV
had PHP 8.3 configured and we are set with that. So the extension does all the setup. The setup
can be done manually without that as well but it works really very well and it sets up our there's
not really anything to set up but it does what we need to do with Xdebug and that sort of thing.
So what I'm going to do now is just demonstrate visiting a project with Xdebug going. So we will
we will set up here if I can get to it from my tools. I have to get these tools out of the way
or I can't get to it here. Let me just try this. There we go. I'm going to say start listening
for PHP. So this is the way Xdebug works is that the IDE listens for a network connection
and then the code the PHP code contacts the IDE to tell it what's going on with the bugging.
So on the IDE we told it to listen. Now let's make a let's make a breakpoint here and I am going to
I am going to do a `ddev xdebug on` to tell debug to do ddev to start doing its thing and let's remember
what our project is our project is d11.ddev.site. So I can do a `ddev launch` for example or I can
just visit in the browser either way and you see that it launched it here and it's sitting there
and why is it sitting there it's sitting there because PhpStorm got the message stopped at the
breakpoint is showing us the variables that are available there and it is ready to go so I can
now step through I can use an F8 to step through I can use a F7 to step in here and step through
all of my things and there I'm there I'm set so PhpStorm was awfully easy to set that up with
I'm going to use an F9 to say go ahead and finish this off the all the things that we needed to do
were done so that's how Xdebug works with PhpStorm and that's how PhpStorm works in a WSL2
environment so let's go ahead and do the same thing now with we'll do the same thing with VS Code
so I am going to exit here and now I will try with VS Code let's just see what our situation is
so we have a fair starting place I might as well do in that `ddev xdebug off`. Xdebug doesn't cost as much
in performance these days as it once did but most people turn it on when they want it and turn it
off when they don't want it again so let's go ahead and do the same thing now with with
VS Code so the way you start a WSL2 instance in VS Code is in your project here we are in the d11
project in your project we do a code dot that's basically saying VS Code launch a VS Code that
understands WSL2 using the current directory so that's installing the VS Code server
there's a very easy way to pop this up and now it's running it here with the regular windows side
VS Code interface that we need so now we need to include a couple of this is this is a clean more
or less clean we'll see how clean it is we need to install a couple of extensions here so let's get
our extensions we I imagine it's already got the WSL because that's how it works and now we need
the PHP extension the PHP debug extension is what we're going to need the official one unfortunately
it's very confusing how many different ones there can be but this is the one from Xdebug.org that's
the one that we want so we'll get the PHP debug and and we're going to install it in our WSL world
as well so we want that and then let's get the DDEV to DDEV extension so we're it's the DDEV
manager that we want there's other one you see the old logo we don't know the history of that one
but it is obsolete so we're going to take the DDEV manager and install that in WSL
I don't know what happened to our PHP debug let's see WSL is required to open the remote window
okay we got the DDEV manager
not it looks like we got oh here we need the PHP debug we need that installed in WSL
okay that looks like it probably good now let's go use the I'm not I don't have the same
amount of experience with VS Code as I do with the jet brains i.e.s so I may stumble a little bit
here but let's go to the explorer we're doing here exactly the same thing as we were doing elsewhere
we can go to the install.tex we can go to the index.php here and here's our index.php
and this is saying that the PHP executable path isn't set that I think our DDEV
extension should have done that for us but let's see what happens here I'm going to just set
breakpoint just like we did in PhpStorm and I'm going to use the terminal here
so terminal works exactly the same let's get rid of this and you see that the the terminal
is working very well it's also again in the distro and do DDEV list `ddev xdebug on`
and so now in VS Code we have to tell it to run a debug so it was say run a debug
and then you have to say listen for Xdebug and there it is you see this orange bar down here
is the indicator that it is actually listening properly I find this a little awkward having to
click here and then click here but we'll do that and now we're going to do the exact same thing
we'll go back and in the terminal we'll do a DDEV launch it's the same as just visiting the page
on the project and you see it paused here it's waiting to load it would have been long since done
loading but the VS Code wants to run well it stopped on our breakpoint and up here are the variables
that are running at that point and again here we can use the just pull this down just a
little bit we can we can step in to a function call we can step over a function call
and we have and it shows the it has little hints there f8 shift f8 you can do all the things
that you would expect to do with your debugger so in both PhpStorm and
nVS Code have database capabilities and all kinds of other things but and they do get for you
I don't approve of that I think huge get from the command line person I'm a big believer that you
know more what's going on when you do that but that's for another time but both PhpStorm and
VS Code will do get for you and do all the things and let's see where we are now so we just did
without any incident we just did VS Code so there was our PhpStorm step debugging here's our VS Code
step-debugging and we we installed the extensions that we needed we did the code we did the `code .`
did a ``ddev xdebug on``, did the VS Code listen thing and we visited a page and it stopped which is
pretty stinking cool so okay let's go back and just talk about a couple of things that you might
have questions about you have heard about docker desktop for years now and so what about docker
desktop did have has supported docker desktop on both traditional windows and wsl2 for many years
and it it works fine the installer as you saw when we went through the installer it was
offering both of those docker desktop is commercial software and it has a very specific license
agreement and your company may need to pay for you to be able to use it they're very strict about it
and docker desktop unfortunately is not really very stable it seems to have new bugs and every
release so compared to docker CE which is Linux based and very very well maintained by the same
company I might add this is a company that we are very indebted to docker ink maintains all of
these wonderful open source tools that we depend on that are components of every docker provider
but docker desktop is not their finest hour it's focused on a lot of things that are not just
doing the jobs that we need to do so docker desktop is fully supported if you would prefer to use
that it's a little more complicated than what we just did but not much and then what about
traditional windows so traditional windows is just the label that we give of if you're working on
windows and the regular windows ntfs file system we just call that traditional windows as opposed
to the various wsl2 approaches and we've supported it for many years the performance is not as good as
with wsl2 and there's some initial startup sync time on a project that you may or may not find
troublesome but in reality it's not bad it used to be terrible it used to be just you know when
we first did wsl2 traditional windows was something that you would never want to do anymore because
wsl2 is so much better but now the traditional windows has mutagen support
it's actually tolerable and some teams use that deliberately because their teams are familiar with
get basher power shell or cmd and so they do what they need to do there so there was a time
than we that we were threatening to deprecate this approach and we have about 5% of our users that
are on traditional windows and they're very defensive about that so we won't do that anymore plus
it works a lot better than it used to okay so let's just take a quick look at what we did make sure
that we that we know what it was so we talked about what ddev is what wsl2 is on windows and why we'd
want to use it the advantages and disadvantages which are almost the same thing you get Linux you get
Linux we did the install which is just three steps that shows on ddev.com slash get started we
installed wsl on our machine which is just a one-time thing and then we ran the the installer
and then we created a project that's what we did then so here's the dummy project that we did
and we did we demonstrated some of the commands then we demonstrated accessing wsl2 project
from PhpStorm and doing xt bug on it and then VS Code accessing it which is a little different
using the code dot approach from inside your distro and then we talked about docker desktop and
traditional windows and here we are with the resources for you obviously ddev.com has all the
things and pointers to all the things but one of those things is the ddev docs and in there you'll
find the wsl2 install docs in more detail there's a great drupal.org tutorial on all this and don't
forget about the Microsoft docs at learn.microsoft.com and we would love to have you join us for support
discussion learning from you discussing the problems that you have and everything else
at in discord on stack overflow and the ddev issue queue and our project repo of course is
github.com slash ddev slash ddev so join us we would love to have you and thanks for hanging
with me today.